<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ModMetaData>
  <name>WorkRoles</name>
  <author>Morten Mertner</author>
  <packageId>mnmr.workroles</packageId>
  <supportedVersions>
    <li>1.6</li>
  </supportedVersions>
  <modDependencies>
    <li>
      <packageId>brrainz.harmony</packageId>
      <displayName>Harmony</displayName>
      <steamWorkshopUrl>steam://url/CommunityFilePage/2009463077</steamWorkshopUrl>
    </li>
  </modDependencies>
  <loadAfter>
    <li>brrainz.harmony</li>
  </loadAfter>
  <incompatibleWith>
    <li>fluffy.worktab</li>
    <li>arof.fluffy.worktab</li>
    <li>arof.fluffy.worktab.continued</li>
    <li>natee.EnhancedWorkTab</li>
  </incompatibleWith>
  <description>WorkRoles replaces the Work tab with role-based work management. No more number grids: define roles as ordered lists of jobs, stack them on your colonists, and let ordering decide who does what first. Whether you run a three-pawn camp or a sprawling colony, roles make work assignments readable, reusable and quick to change.

Key Features:
- Roles, Not Numbers: A role is an ordered list of jobs — whole work types like Cooking, or single jobs like "smelt". A colonist's roles combine into one clear work order: earlier roles win, and within a role, earlier jobs win. If no role mentions a job, the colonist never does it.
- Overlapping Roles: The same job can live in multiple roles, and a colonist can hold both. Keep an "Emergency Harvest" role sharing Farmer's jobs assigned to half the colony at high priority but disabled — when blight or a cold snap hits, one click re-tasks everyone to the fields.
- One-Click Situational Control: Toggle any role globally (everyone holding it adapts instantly) or per colonist, without touching the underlying assignments.
- Ready-Made Setup: 17 color-coded roles (Doctor, Farmer, Grunt, ...) covering every vanilla and DLC work type. Adding the mod to an existing save converts current priorities into matching role sets automatically.
- Drag &amp; Drop Everything: Drag roles onto colonists, reorder with a drop marker, move roles between pawns — per-pawn state travels along.
- Smart Recommendations: A per-colonist panel suggests roles from burning passions, gene aptitudes, colony-best skills and training opportunities — click to assign, or "Make It So" for all of them. Skills, passions and aptitudes are shown alongside.
- Deep Job Control: The role editor's filterable job tree works like the storage filter — check a whole work type or individual jobs, then reorder them freely, including specific jobs above a catch-all.
- Copy &amp; Paste: Transfer complete role sets between colonists, disabled states included.
- Modded Jobs Just Work: Work types and jobs added by other mods appear automatically — no compatibility patches needed.
- Multiplayer Ready: Full RimWorld Multiplayer support — every role edit and assignment is synced.

Compatibility:
- Work Tab Mods: Not compatible with other mods that replace the Work tab (Fluffy's Work Tab forks, Better Work Tab, Enhanced Work Tab).
- Save Compatible: Safe to add to existing saves (priorities convert to roles) and safe to remove (the vanilla Work tab comes back sensibly populated).
- Requires Harmony.</description>
</ModMetaData>
